import { useReducer, useEffect, useContext, createContext } from "react";

// Predefined questions array

  const questionsData = [
    {
      "question": "Which is the most popular JavaScript framework?",
      "options": ["Angular", "React", "Svelte", "Vue"],
      "correctOption": 1,
      "points": 20
    },
    {
      "question": "Which company invented React?",
      "options": ["Google", "Apple", "Netflix", "Facebook"],
      "correctOption": 3,
      "points": 20
    },
    {
      "question": "What's the fundamental building block of React apps?",
      "options": ["Components", "Blocks", "Elements", "Effects"],
      "correctOption": 0,
      "points": 20
    },
    {
      "question": "What's the name of the syntax we use to describe the UI in React components?",
      "options": ["FBJ", "Babel", "JSX", "ES2015"],
      "correctOption": 2,
      "points": 20
    },
    {
      "question": "How does data flow naturally in React apps?",
      "options": [
        "From parents to children",
        "From children to parents",
        "Both ways",
        "The developers decides"
      ],
      "correctOption": 0,
      "points": 20
    },
    {
      "question": "How to pass data into a child component?",
      "options": ["State", "Props", "PropTypes", "Parameters"],
      "correctOption": 1,
      "points": 20
    },
    {
      "question": "When to use derived state?",
      "options": [
        "Whenever the state should not trigger a re-render",
        "Whenever the state can be synchronized with an effect",
        "Whenever the state should be accessible to all components",
        "Whenever the state can be computed from another state variable"
      ],
      "correctOption": 3,
      "points": 20
    },
    {
      "question": "What triggers a UI re-render in React?",
      "options": [
        "Running an effect",
        "Passing props",
        "Updating state",
        "Adding event listeners to DOM elements"
      ],
      "correctOption": 2,
      "points": 20
    },
    {
      "question": "When do we directly \"touch\" the DOM in React?",
      "options": [
        "When we need to listen to an event",
        "When we need to change the UI",
        "When we need to add styles",
        "Almost never"
      ],
      "correctOption": 3,
      "points": 20
    },
    {
      "question": "In what situation do we use a callback to update state?",
      "options": [
        "When updating the state will be slow",
        "When the updated state is very data-intensive",
        "When the state update should happen faster",
        "When the new state depends on the previous state"
      ],
      "correctOption": 3,
      "points": 20
    },
    {
      "question": "If we pass a function to useState, when will that function be called?",
      "options": [
        "On each re-render",
        "Each time we update the state",
        "Only on the initial render",
        "The first time we update the state"
      ],
      "correctOption": 2,
      "points": 20
    },
    {
      "question": "Which hook to use for an API request on the component's initial render?",
      "options": ["useState", "useEffect", "useRef", "useReducer"],
      "correctOption": 1,
      "points": 20
    },
    {
      "question": "Which variables should go into the useEffect dependency array?",
      "options": [
        "Usually none",
        "All our state variables",
        "All state and props referenced in the effect",
        "All variables needed for clean up"
      ],
      "correctOption": 2,
      "points": 20
    },
    {
      "question": "An effect will always run on the initial render.",
      "options": [
        "True",
        "It depends on the dependency array",
        "False",
        "In depends on the code in the effect"
      ],
      "correctOption": 0,
      "points": 20
    },
    {
      "question": "When will an effect run if it doesn't have a dependency array?",
      "options": [
        "Only when the component mounts",
        "Only when the component unmounts",
        "The first time the component re-renders",
        "Each time the component is re-rendered"
      ],
      "correctOption": 3,
      "points": 20
    }
  ]



const initialState = {
  questions: [],
  status: 'loading',
  index: 0,
  answer: null,
  points: 0,
  highscore: 0,
  secondsRemaining: null,
};

const QuizContext = createContext();

const SECS_PER_QUESTIONS = 30;

function reducer(state, action) {
  switch (action.type) {
    case 'dataReceived':
      return {
        ...state,
        questions: action.payload,
        status: 'ready',
      };
    case 'dataFailed':
      return {
        ...state,
        status: 'error',
      };
    case 'start':
      return { ...state, status: "active", secondsRemaining: state.questions.length * SECS_PER_QUESTIONS };
    case 'newAnswer':
      const question = state.questions.at(state.index);
      return {
        ...state,
        answer: action.payload,
        points: action.payload === question.correctOption ? state.points + question.points : state.points,
      };
    case 'nextQuestion':
      return { ...state, index: state.index + 1, answer: null };
    case 'Finish':
      return { ...state, status: 'finished', highscore: state.points > state.highscore ? state.points : state.highscore };
    case 'tick':
      return { ...state, secondsRemaining: state.secondsRemaining - 1, status: state.secondsRemaining === 0 ? 'finished' : state.status };
    case 'restart':
      return { ...initialState, questions: state.questions, highscore: state.highscore, status: 'ready' };
    default:
      return state;
  }
}

function QuizProvider({ children }) {
  const [{ questions, status, index, answer, points, highscore, secondsRemaining }, dispatch] = useReducer(reducer, initialState);

  useEffect(() => {
    // Simulating fetch by directly dispatching the data
    dispatch({ type: 'dataReceived', payload: questionsData });
  }, []);

  return (
    <QuizContext.Provider value={{ questions, status, index, answer, points, highscore, secondsRemaining, dispatch }}>
      {children}
    </QuizContext.Provider>
  );
}

function useQuiz() {
  const context = useContext(QuizContext);
  if (context === undefined)
    throw new Error("QuizContext was used outside of the QuizProvider");
  return context;
}

export { QuizProvider, useQuiz };
